{"tossups": [{"question": "The merger of the Sveno and the Bolshevik Workers Party into the Fatherland Front overthrew this nation's monarchy following a Soviet invasion. This European nation lost the Second Balkan War against its former allies of Serbia and Greece, losing territory in Macedonia and Thrace. Tsars such as Ferdinand I and Boris III led, for ten points, what member of the Axis governed from the city of Sofia?", "answer": "Tsardom of <b><u>Bulgaria</u></b> (or Tsarstvo <b><u>Balgariya</u></b>; accept \"Kingdom\" in place of \"Tsardom\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Lesser-known theories for the start of this event include a game of craps or possibly even a meteor shower. The two original scapegoats for this event were finally cleared of responsibility in 1997 by a city council, 126 years after this event took place. Several buildings, such as St. James Cathedral and Unity Church, survived this event although not without scorch marks. For ten points, name this 1871 disaster, legendarily started by Mrs. O'Leary's cow.", "answer": "Great <b><u>Chicago Fire</u></b> of 1871", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "At Thalamae [[THAL-ah-mee]], a cult center dedicated to a queen of this island named Pasipha\u00eb [[PASS-if-fee]] was a pilgrimage site for travelers seeking an oracle. A king of this realm named Deucalion [[doo-KAY-lee-on]] was slain by the departing Theseus outside the gates of Knossos [[kuh-NAH-sus]], which was a major site of a Bronze Age civilization on this island. The Minoans once ruled, for ten points, what Aegean Island?", "answer": "<b><u>Crete</u></b> (or <b><u>Kriti</u></b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "The name for this object was suggested by an eleven-year old, and other suggested names for it were Zeus and Percival. When this heavenly body was discovered by Clyde Tombaugh in 1930, it disproved Percival Lowell's Planet X theory. Neil deGrasse Tyson said that allowing this object to be a planet would be an \"insult\" to the other planets. For ten points, name this trans-Neptunian dwarf planet in the Kuiper [[KY-per]] Belt that was once called the \"Ninth Planet\".", "answer": "<b><u>Pluto</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "In 1980, this man sent a large number of criminals and mental patients among a group of dissidents allowed to leave his country in the Mariel boatlift. In 1961, the Democratic Revolutionary Front launched a disastrous attempt to overthrow this man known as the \"Bay of Pigs\" invasion. Two years earlier, this man took power after deposing Fulgencio Batista [[ful-JEN-syoh bah-TEE-stah]] with the aid of Che Guevara [[cheh geh-VAH-rah]]. For ten points, name this revolutionary who was the dictator of communist Cuba from 1959 to 2008.", "answer": "Fidel <b><u>Castro</u></b> (or Fidel Alejandro <b><u>Castro</u></b> Ruz)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man earned the nickname \"Greekling\" for his flamboyant nature and love of Plato. This man was criticized for mourning openly after his beloved Antinous [[an-TIN-oh-us]] drowned in the Nile in 130 A.D. This man's primary supporter and aunt, Pompeia Plotina [[pom-PAY-ah ploh-TYE-nah]], supposedly hired someone to impersonate her husband Trajan to appoint this man as Trajan's successor. For ten points, name this member of the \"Five Good Emperors\" who built a namesake wall across Britannia.", "answer": "<b><u>Hadrian</u></b> (accept Caesar Traianus <b><u>Hadrian</u></b>us)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "As a lawyer, this man worked on Senator John Smith's expulsion case and served as Sam Houston's attorney after the latter caned William Stanbery. This man's most famous effort came during an episode in which he was a dinner guest to Vice Admiral Alexander Cochrane [[\"COCK\"-rin]] aboard the HMS <em>Tonnant</em>. This man composed a song to the tune of \"To Anacreon in Heaven\" during the bombardment of Fort McHenry. For ten points, name this American composer of \"The Star-Spangled Banner.\"", "answer": "Francis Scott <b><u>Key</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Nominoe became the first king of this region after he and his local Vannetais tribe supported Louis the Pious in the fight against his sibling Lothair. A duchess of this region name Anne of Monfort commissioned the tapestry <em>Hunt of the Unicorn</em> to commemorate her marriage to Louis XII [[the twelfth]]. This region, known as <em>Breizh</em> [[BREHSH]] in its native Celtic tongue, was ruled by Henry II son's Geoffrey from the city of Rennes [[REN]].The Edict of Nantes was signed in, for ten points, what region of Northwestern France?", "answer": "<b><u>Brittany</u></b> (accept <b><u>Breizh</u></b> before mentioned; Accept <b><u>Bretagne</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In the Neolithic period on this island, a group of standing stones likely meant to evoke fertility were rearranged by the Torrean [[toh-REH-ahn]] people at the Filitosa [[fee-lee-TOH-sah]] site. This island, which the launching point of the pro-De Gaulle Operation Resurrection, was ruled for nearly five hundred years by a republic in Liguria. The site of the Maison Bonaparte, the birthplace of Napoleon, for ten points, what is this French island department?", "answer": "<b><u>Corsica</u></b> (or <b><u>Corse</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Judy Clarke has been nicknamed \u201cSt. Jude\u201d for her work in preventing this practice. <em>Furman v. Georgia</em> put a moratorium on this practice until the states could demonstrate they were no longer arbitrary or discriminatory in how this practice was done. <em>Atkins v. Virginia</em> ruled that the intellectually disabled could not undergo this punitive practice, which was applied to the Rosenbergs and Timothy McVeigh. For ten points, name this practice that was often accomplished with the electric chair.", "answer": "<b><u>Capital Punishment</u></b> [accept the <b><u>Death Penalty</u></b>; or <b><u>Executions</u></b>; or <b><u>Killing</u> </b>Prisoners)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Though officially called the Revolutionary Nuns, a \"Guard\" nicknamed for this legendary culture served under Muammar Gaddafi of Libya. Strabo [[STRAY-boh]] claimed that these people lived along the Thermodon [[THER-moh-don]] River though they had retreated beyond the realm of the Gargareans [[gar-GAR-ee-ans]] with whom these people reproduced children. Legendarily led by Penthesilea [[pen-theh-sih-LAY-uh]] during the Attic War, for ten points, what was this culture of warrior women who may have lived in Scythia [[SIH-thee-ah]]?", "answer": "<b><u>Amazon</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Amazon</u></b>ian Guard)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "A \u201cRenaissance\u201d among these people followed the overthrow of the Gutians [[GOO-tee-ans]]. The Stele [[STEE-lee]] of the Vultures commemorates the victory of Lagash [[LAY-gash]] over Umma, both cities founded by these people. Scenes of war and daily life are shown on the Standard of Ur, created by these people. These people were the first to build step-pyramid temples called ziggurats. For ten points, name this earliest civilization to spring up in Mesopotamia.", "answer": "<b><u>Sumer</u></b>ians", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "The constitution of this nation that was in place until 1987 was written by U.S. Assistant Secretary of the Navy, Franklin D. Roosevelt. After this country's president ordered the mass execution of prisoners in 1915, he was killed by a mob, leading to a U.S. occupation. Toussaint L'Ouverture [[too-SAHN loh-vehr-TOOR]] is known as the father of this country for leading it to independence. For ten points, name this country whose President Jovenel Mo\u00efse [[jove-NEL moh-EEZ]] was assassinated in 2021.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Haiti</u></b> (or Republique d'<b><u>Haiti</u></b>; or Repiblik d <b><u>Ayiti</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The preaching background of this party's first leader led Morgan Phillips to comment, \"Socialism in Britain owed more to Methodism than Marx.\" That founder of this party, Keir Hardie, resigned in favor of Arthur Henderson, who won the Nobel Peace Prize for chairing the Geneva Disarmament Conference. This party interrupted Winston Churchill's term as prime minister under the leadership of Clement Attlee. For ten points, name this currently center-left British political party, the opponent of the Conservatives.", "answer": "<b><u>Labour</u></b> Party", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In the Spring and Autumn Annals, this specific term is used to refer to anyone living in the \"Outside Land\" beyond the realm of imperial China. This English word derives from an ancient Greek antonym for \"citizen\" and was used to describe all non-Greeks because their languages supposedly sounded like gibberish. For ten points, name this pejorative term, which the Romans used to refer to any \"uncivilized\" tribal groups beyond their borders.", "answer": "<b><u>Barbar</u></b>ians (accept <b><u>BarBar</u></b>; or <b><u>Barbar</u></b>os; or <b><u>Barbar</u></b>ism; accept <b><u>Yi</u></b>; prompt on \"uncivilized,\" \"savage\", or any other synonymous terms)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Anthropology"}, {}, {"question": "In the hopes of helping a certain species avoid the plague, scientists performed this procedure on a black-footed ferret named Willa. Early steps towards understanding this process included the discovery of embryotic induction by German scientist Hans Spemann [[SHPEH-mahn]]. The Roslin Institute in Scotland managed to perform this process on a mammal for the first time with a sheep named Dolly. For ten points, name this biological process of producing organisms with matching DNA.", "answer": "<b><u>Cloning</u></b> (accept <b><u>Clone</u></b>s)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {}, {"question": "An annual festival featuring the mock tarring and feathering of a tax collector in Washington County celebrates this uprising. A leader during this event, James McFarlane, was shot and killed at the Battle of Bower Hill. The \"Watermelon Army\" was led into battle by a sitting president for the only time in U.S. history during this uprising. For ten points, identify this rebellion of the 1790s against a tax on a specific kind of alcohol.", "answer": "<b><u>Whiskey</u></b> Rebellion (accept \"Revolt\" or \"Insurrection\" for \"Rebellion\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This U.S. armed forces branch traces its history to a force raised by Samuel Nicholas, who, with Esek Hopkins, orchestrated the capture of Nassau. This branch claims that their dress uniform's \"blood stripe\" memorializes the fallen at Chapultepec [[CHAH-puhl-TEH-pek]] Castle. This branch was led by Presley O'Bannon in one battle, which is immortalized in its namesake \"Hymn.\" For ten points, name this U.S. armed forces branch that has fought \"from the halls of Montezuma to the shores of Tripoli.\"", "answer": "United States <b><u>Marine</u></b> Corps (accept US<b><u>MC</u></b>; accept United States <b><u>Marine</u></b>s)  In the Pacific Campaign of World War Two, the United States Marine corps was instrumental to the success of this strategy, in which heavily fortified Japanese islands were simply avoided in favor of cutting them off from supplies, reducing the overall loss of soldiers.  ANSWER: <b><u>Leapfrog</u></b>ging (or <b><u>Island Hop</u></b>ping)  <b> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>These people erected a namesake \"Stele\" [[STEE-lee]] in modern Xi'an [[SHEE-</u><u>AHN]] written in both Chinese and Syriac. Two holy men of this faith supposedly</u></b> <b><u>smuggled silkworms out of China and brought them to the court of Justinian the</u></b> <b><u>Great. Hong (+)</u> Xiuquan [[SHU-CHWAN]], the leader of the Taiping Rebellion, claimed to be the younger brother of this faith's (*) </b>messiah. Matteo Ricci [[REE-chee]] visited China as a Jesuit missionary of, for ten points, which Abrahamic faith?", "answer": "Chinese <b><u>Christian</u></b>s (or <b><u>Christian</u></b>ity; accept <b><u>Catholic</u></b>ism; accept <b><u>Nestorian</u></b>ism; do not accept \"Eastern Orthodox Christianity\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Henry the Lion's \"Artlenburger privilege\" founded a predecessor of this</u></b> <b><u>organization called the Gotlander Cooperative. This organization had its trading</u></b> <b><u>privileges with England returned following the 15th century Treaty of (+)</u> Utrecht after a prolonged campaign of commerce raiding. This dominant power of the Baltic and North Sea trade routes included cities like (*) </b>Hamburg and L\u00fcbeck. For ten points, name this \"League\" of German cities, a maritime power of the late Middles Ages.", "answer": "<b><u>Hanseatic</u></b> League (accept the <b><u>Hanse</u></b>; or <b><u>Hansa</u></b>; accept Deutsche <b><u>Hanse</u></b>; accept <b><u>Gotlander Cooperative</u></b> before \"predecessor\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Several members of this party who opposed a provisional constitution of</u></b> <b><u>Massachusetts were derisively called the Essex Junto. Timothy Pickering and Josiah</u></b> <b><u>Quincy, members of this party, proposed secession for one region during the Hartford</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Convention. This party's only official member who became president signed the Alien and Sedition Acts into law and served after (*) </b>George Washington. For ten points, name this party of John Adams which opposed the Jeffersonians.", "answer": "<b><u>Federalist</u></b> Party (or <b><u>Federalist</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This conflict saw the \"Border Ruffians\" engage in electoral fraud, with one of</u></b> <b><u>its leaders depicted in the painting \"Tragic Prelude.\" This conflict, derived from</u></b> <b><u>popular sovereignty, saw James Buchanan support a \"Lecompton\" constitution. After</u></b> <b><u>Charles Sumner was (+)</u> caned for speaking against this event, radical abolitionists killed five people in the (*) </b>Pottawatomie Massacre. For ten points, name this conflict during James Buchanan's presidency over whether a Midwestern state would adopt slavery.", "answer": "<b><u>Bleeding Kansas</u></b> (accept <b><u>Bloody Kansas</u></b> or the <b><u>Kansas Border War</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Details of this event were first revealed in an anonymous letter sent to</u></b> <b><u>William Parker, 4th Baron Monteagle. Some of the men involved in planning this</u></b> <b><u>event battled the Sheriff of Worcester [[WOO-ster]] at Holbeche [[\"HOLE\"-beech]]</u></b> <b><u>House, where this event\u2019s leader, (+)</u> Robert Catesby [[KATES-bee]], was killed. Eight of the conspirators involved in this event were convicted at a subsequent trial, including (*) </b>Guy Fawkes. For ten points, name this failed plan to destroy the House of Lords and assassinate King James I.", "answer": "<b><u>Gunpowder Plot</u></b> (or <b><u>Gunpowder</u></b> Treason <b><u>Plot</u></b>; accept <b><u>Jesuit Treason</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Indian grammarian Panini developed a system of this field that bears</u></b> <b><u>similarities to a type created by the author of</u> </b><em><b><u>The Laws of Thought</u></b></em><b><u>. Used in a</u></b> <b><u>namesake type of algebra, this branch's Boolean (*)</u> form uses values like </b><em><b>true</b></em><b> and </b><em><b>false</b></em><b>. The syllogism was developed by Aristotle while studying this field of thought. (*) </b>For ten points, name this philosophical field with applications in math and computer science, the informal type of which studies the validity of arguments.", "answer": "<b><u>Logic</u></b> (accept Boolean <b><u>Logic</u></b>; accept <b><u>Pramana</u></b>; accept <b><u>Anviksiki</u></b>; accept Formal or Informal <b><u>Logic</u></b>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "<b><u>Like his Russian cousin some years later, this man received a dragon tattoo on</u></b> <b><u>his arm while visiting Japan in 1881. During this man's rule, the Parliament Act</u></b> <b><u>cemented the House of Commons' superiority to the House of Lords, and the Free</u></b> <b><u>State of Ireland became (*)</u> independent. This man's tour of gravesites in Belgium was memorialized in Rudyard Kipling's long poem </b><em><b>The King's Pilgrimage</b></em><b>. (*) </b>For ten points, name this ruler of Great Britain during World War One.", "answer": "<b><u>George V</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A man named Antipholus [[ahn-TEH-foh-lus]] and his servant Dromio, both</u></b> <b><u>residents of this island, travel to Ephesus [[eh-FUH-sus]] in search of their respective</u></b> <b><u>twins in the Shakespearean play</u> </b><em><b><u>The Comedy of Errors</u></b></em><b><u>. Italian writer Luigi Pirandello</u></b> <b><u>wrote his play (*)</u> </b><em><b>Six Character's in Search of an Author</b></em><b> in this island's native dialect. Johann Wolfgang von Goethe [[GUR-tuh]] wrote a travelogue about climbing Mt. (*) </b>Etna on, for ten points, what southern Italian island?", "answer": "<b><u>Sicily</u></b> (accept <b><u>Sicilia</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Drama"}, {"question": "<b><u>A section of this region is named for a British ship expedition captained by</u></b> <b><u>George Nares which first sounded the depths of this region in 1875. Don Walsh and</u></b> <b><u>Jacques Piccard were the first to descend into this region in the</u> </b><em><b><u>Trieste</u></b></em><b><u>. (+)</u> This region was designated a U.S. National Monument in 2009, and in 2012 James Cameron performed a solo descent into its (*) </b>lowest point, Challenger Deep. For ten points, name this crescent-shaped Pacific Ocean trench, the deepest in the world.", "answer": "<b><u>Mariana</u></b>s Trench (accept <b><u>Challenger</u></b> Deep before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}], "bonuses": []}